<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Logging | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/logging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-20T16:16:20+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Import Data to Graphite From Munin]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/28/import-data-to-graphite-from-munin/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-28T18:26:44+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/28/import-data-to-graphite-from-munin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To convert data from munin/rrd to graphite/whisper you need to use the <code>rrdwhisper</code> tool which in centos is part of the python-whisper package.</p>

<p>If you want to change the data retention/resolution properties in graphite you will also need to resize the files as well.</p>

<p>Note that Graphites reads from /etc/carbon/storage-aggregation.conf and /etc/carbon/storage-schemas.conf to select the retention and aggregation policies for <em>new</em> data, but since these are set in the file at creation time editing the config file has no effect on existing files (or those created with whisper2rrd).</p>

<p>Recent data is stored at 10 second intervals, when it becomes older 6 lots of 10 second data get aggregated to make a one minute interval. I think this aggregation also happens on newer data if I select say data for the last 2 days since this time period include data at the lower resolution - all the data I get is at this lower resolution.</p>

<p>When this data is aggregated it can be averaged; in my case I&rsquo;m measuring how long something takes - and average is right. But say I was counting something then I&rsquo;d want to know the total over a minute - sum - not average, and if I was recording peaks then I&rsquo;d want the max.</p>

<p>The xFilesFactor as I understand it tells graphite to ignore all the data for an interval if there are too many nulls, but since my original data is at a lower resolution I have loads of nulls and don&rsquo;t want to ignore anything - so I&rsquo;m setting this to zero and my import seems to work well at different scales and on both old and new data.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">
for rrd in *rrd ; do 
    rrd2whisper --xFilesFactor=0.0 --aggregationMethod=average $rrd
    whisper-resize  --xFilesFactor=0.0 --aggregationMethod=average --nobackup ${rrd%.rrd}_42.wsp   10s:6h 1min:6d 10min:1800d  
done


[ -d /var/lib/carbon/whisper/munin ] || sudo -u carbon mkdir -p /var/lib/carbon/whisper/munin
sudo mv *wsp /var/lib/carbon/whisper/munin
sudo chown -R carbon:carbon  /var/lib/carbon/whisper/munin
</code></pre>

<p>This script excerpt deals with the basic conversion - I also needed to convert the long filenames munin used to a nested directory structure used by graphite.</p>

<p>That conversion will depend on your use case - if you look at the files stored under /var/lib/carbon/whisper and /var/lib/munin you should be able to see the pattern.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Log From Jmeter to Statsd]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/25/how-to-log-from-jmeter-to-statsd/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-25T19:57:40+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/25/how-to-log-from-jmeter-to-statsd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to log from Jmeter to statsd you need to add <a href="https://github.com/tim-group/java-statsd-client/releases/download/v3.0.1/java-statsd-client-3.0.1.jar">a statsd library</a> to the jmeter /lib path</p>

<p>Then have a beanshell on the thread group setup a statsd object for use by the threads</p>

<p>store this in the props variable - JMeterProperties (class java.util.Properties)</p>

<p>Note that <a href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/util/Properties.html">the docs</a> say</p>

<blockquote><p>Because Properties inherits from Hashtable, the put and putAll methods can be applied to a Properties object. Their use is strongly discouraged as they allow the caller to insert entries whose keys or values are not Strings. The setProperty method should be used instead. If the store or save method is called on a &ldquo;compromised&rdquo; Properties object that contains a non-String key or value, the call will fail. Similarly, the call to the propertyNames or list method will fail if it is called on a &ldquo;compromised&rdquo; Properties object that contains a non-String key.</p></blockquote>

<p>However I didn&rsquo;t find a better place to put the statsd object yet since the ctx variable is thread specific</p>

<pre><code class="java">import com.timgroup.statsd.StatsDClient;
import com.timgroup.statsd.NonBlockingStatsDClient;

StatsDClient statsd = new NonBlockingStatsDClient("jmeter.test", "statsd.exapmle.com", 8125);

props.put("statsd", statsd);
</code></pre>

<p>Now on the Sampler you want to record data for add a beanshell post processor</p>

<p>You can retrieve the statsd connection from the props variable, and obtain the request time taken from the prev variable which is a org.apache.jmeter.samplers.SampleResult</p>

<p>Once we have the pieces together logging the request time to statsd is simple</p>

<pre><code class="java">
import com.timgroup.statsd.StatsDClient;
import com.timgroup.statsd.NonBlockingStatsDClient;

StatsDClient statsd = (StatsDClient) props.get("statsd");
statsd.recordExecutionTime("loadtime", prev.getTime());
</code></pre>

<p>I&rsquo;ve put an example test plan on github <a href="https://github.com/practicalweb/jmeter-statsd-demo">https://github.com/practicalweb/jmeter-statsd-demo</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
