<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Web Development | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/web-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-25T20:03:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Website Costs, Fixed Price, and Bugs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/08/04/website-costs-fixed-price-and-bugs/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/08/04/website-costs-fixed-price-and-bugs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Three interesting posts I&#8217;ve read recently
</p>


<p>
http://www.contenthere.net/2009/08/fixed-bid-implementation-work-a-marriage-made-in-vegas.html
</p>


<p>
Large fixed bid projects are very hard to get right.
</p>


<p>
http://www.teamlalala.com/blog/2008/11/12/how-much-do-websites-cost/
</p>


<p>
How much do websites cost? Well it&#8217;s hard to say.
</p>


<p>
http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001239.html
</p>


<p>
You&#8217;re gonna have bugs - plan for it and log them so that you can analyse the most common ones and  target your budget effectively.  
</p>


<p>
Developing websites is a real challenge, and putting a business process around it so that all parties make a fair profit is hard too. 
</p>


<p>
But it&#8217;s an exciting business to be in and there are profits to be made. 
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IE6 on VirtualBox - Installing the Network Driver]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2008/11/02/ie6-on-virtualbox-installing-the-network-driver/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2008/11/02/ie6-on-virtualbox-installing-the-network-driver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
One of the trial of web development is ensuring that your site works across a range of browsers.
</p>


<p>
Standards compliance is an important part of this - but testing cannot be avoided.
</p>


<p>
I work on Ubuntu, and use VirtualBox together with a licensed copy of Windows XP to test in a Windows environment, which also allows me to at least test the Windows version of Safari. 
</p>


<p>
Unfortunately Microsoft&#8217;s decision to tie Internet Explorer closely with the operating system means that it isn&#8217;t possible to install IE6 alongside IE7.  
</p>


<p>
(<a href="http://tredosoft.com/Multiple_IE">Multiple IEs</a> gets close but doesn&#8217;t exactly replicate each version, and isn&#8217;t compatible with the IE developer toolbar)
</p>


<p>
<a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/ie/archive/2006/11/30/ie6-and-ie7-running-on-a-single-machine.aspx%22">Microsoft have recognised the problem</a> and do provide an <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/ie/archive/2006/11/30/ie6-and-ie7-running-on-a-single-machine.aspx">Internet Explorer Application Compatibility VPC Image</a> which allows you to create a virtual Windows with IE6 installed
</p>


<p>
It is possible to <a href="http://blog.mozmonkey.com/2008/vpc-ie6-ie7-ie8-on-mac-os-x/">convert this image for use in VirtualBox</a>
</p>


<p>
But I couldn&#8217;t initially get the network working. What I had missed is that you have to
</p>


<ul>
    <li>go into the VirtualBox settings for this virtual machine </li>
    <li>in the to select the network section </li>
    <li>specify the &quot;PCnet-PCI II (am79C970A)&quot; network adpator </li>
    <li>boot up the vitual machine</li>
    <li>Windows will try and install the Driver</li>
    <li>Specify a location manually</li>
    <li>Browse to D:\32Bit\Windows\3rdParty\AMD_PCnet</li>
</ul>


<p>
The above assumes you have already installed the Guest Additions.
</p>


<p>
This should succesfuly install the network driver - it worked for me.
</p>


<p>
I now have a true copy of IE6 on Ubuntu and can test away.
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
