<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-20T16:16:20+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Safari Books - Bad Redesign]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/11/04/safari-books-bad-redesign/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/11/04/safari-books-bad-redesign</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
I&#8217;ve had an account with O&#8217;Reilly&#8217;s <a href="http://my.safaribooksonline.com/">Safari books</a> on and off for years
</p>


<p>
I&#8217;ve cancelled it before beacuase of design issues that rendered it unworkable for me.
</p>


<p>
This time they have &quot;upgraded&quot; the site from an AJAX based layout which allowed me to choose between &quot;print fidelity&quot; and &quot;HTML view&quot;.
</p>


<p>
The new layout uses Flash to render the pages as they look in print in a scrollable window.
</p>


<p>
I hate this because
</p>


<ul>
    <li>I work on a widescreen laptop with development toolbars and tabs in my browser - this layout of a tall thin view just doesn&#8217;t fit on my screen.</li>
    <li>I can&#8217;t scroll the Safari menu and banner offscreen </li>
    <li>Most of the time I don&#8217;t care too much about formatting I just want to read it and HTML is easier to read</li>
    <li>The scrolling doesn&#8217;t respond to my mousewheel</li>
    <li>I like to get a nice big page of text onscreen and the use the browsers search to quickly home in on the bit I want to read. </li>
</ul>


<p>Oh well - back to books for now and another incentive to try and get the perfect ereader&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web Fonts With @font-face]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/07/17/web-fonts-with-font-face/"/>
    <updated>2009-07-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2009/07/17/web-fonts-with-font-face</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
When the web first started everything was in Times New Roman, black on grey with few images.
</p>


<p>
Things have moved on a long way since then, but there are still very few fonts. I&#8217;ve worked on many sites that have tried to overcome this by various routes.
</p>


<ul>
    <li>Creating an image of headline text in the desired font<br />
    This can look good but offers poor accessibility and it&#8217;s hard to update</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.mikeindustries.com/blog/sifr/">SiFR</a> - uses JavaScript and flash to add fonts<br />
    It can work well - but performs badly if overused, and can cause problems with z-ordering on some systems</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css3-fonts/#the-font-face-rule">@font-face</a> Part of the CSS standard which allows you to provide font files for download.</li>
</ul>


<p>
@font-face has a great deal of potential as the end users browser automatically downloads the font definition and renders whatever font you specify without any plug-ins or even JavaScript required.
</p>


<p>
However, this is actually quite old technology - I tried to use it back in the days of Internet Explorer 5 and Netscape Navigator.
</p>


<p>
Then as now there were competing standards for downloadable font files.
</p>


<p>
At the time both browsers only offered a web specific font format which didn&#8217;t look good enough to use.
</p>


<p>
However; Firefox 3.5 and Safari 4 now support regular TTF and OTF fonts and these look great.
</p>


<p>
There is still the problem that most good fonts are supplied under license - which prevents you providing them for download. 
</p>


<p>
But with two major browsers providing a good implementation for standard font file we can hope that it won&#8217;t be too much longer before the problem is solved. 
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
