<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ubuntu | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/ubuntu/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-16T20:03:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Specifying MTU for a VPN Connection in NetworkManager]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/12/03/specifying-mtu-for-a-vpn-connection-in-networkmanager/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T11:34:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/12/03/specifying-mtu-for-a-vpn-connection-in-networkmanager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I need to use a VPN which was suffering packet fragmentation due to the overhead involved (actually I use a VPN to connect to a network which then has another VPN connection to a third network).</p>

<p>To determine the largest MTU size which didn&rsquo;t lead to fragmentation I just ran variations on</p>

<pre><code class="bash ">ping -M do -s 1327 server.example.com
</code></pre>

<p><code>-M do</code> prohibits fragmentation so the ping will fail if the packet size is too large</p>

<p>I tried larger/ smaller values till I found the largest number that worked.</p>

<p>Network Manager didn&rsquo;t give me a GUI to set MTU on the VPN connection (it does for ethernet)</p>

<p>So I needed a script in /etc/network/if-up.d/</p>

<p>I called mine like myvpn-mtu (owned by root and executable)</p>

<pre><code class="bash">#! /bin/sh
# set low MTU for my VPN otherwise I get packet fragmentation
set -e


if [ "$CONNECTION_ID" = myvpn ] &amp;&amp; [ "$MODE" = start ]; then
  /sbin/ifconfig $IFACE mtu 1327
fi


exit 0
</code></pre>

<p>Substitute &ldquo;myvpn&rdquo; here for your connection name</p>

<p>The script env has the following variables (I&rsquo;ve anonymised some variables)</p>

<pre><code>ADDRFAM=NetworkManager
CONNECTION_ID=xxxxxxxxxxxxxx
CONNECTION_UUID=xxxxxxx-xxxxx-xxxxx-xxxx-xxxxx
DEVICE_IFACE=wlan0
DEVICE_IP_IFACE=wlan0
DHCP4_BROADCAST_ADDRESS=192.168.0.255
DHCP4_DHCP_LEASE_TIME=86400
DHCP4_DHCP_MESSAGE_TYPE=5
DHCP4_DHCP_REBINDING_TIME=75600
DHCP4_DHCP_RENEWAL_TIME=43200
DHCP4_DHCP_SERVER_IDENTIFIER=192.168.0.1
DHCP4_DOMAIN_NAME=xxx
DHCP4_DOMAIN_NAME_SERVERS=192.168.0.1
DHCP4_EXPIRY=1417685250
DHCP4_HOST_NAME=xxx
DHCP4_IP_ADDRESS=192.168.0.209
DHCP4_NETWORK_NUMBER=192.168.0.0
DHCP4_ROUTERS=192.168.0.1
DHCP4_SUBNET_MASK=255.255.255.0
IFACE=tun0
IP4_ADDRESS_0=192.168.0.209/24 192.168.0.1
IP4_DOMAINS=xxx
IP4_NAMESERVERS=192.168.0.1
IP4_NUM_ADDRESSES=1
IP4_NUM_ROUTES=0
LOGICAL=tun0
METHOD=NetworkManager
MODE=start
PHASE=post-up
PWD=/
VERBOSITY=0
VPN_IP4_ADDRESS_0=192.168.1.48/24 x.x.x.x
VPN_IP4_NAMESERVERS=x.x.x.x
VPN_IP4_NUM_ADDRESSES=1
VPN_IP4_NUM_ROUTES=28
VPN_IP4_ROUTE_0=192.168.1.0/24 0.0.0.0 0
VPN_IP4_ROUTE_1=192.168.2.0/24 0.0.0.0 0
VPN_IP4_ROUTE_2=192.168.3.0/24 0.0.0.0 0
VPN_IP4_ROUTE_3=192.168.4.0/24 0.0.0.0 0
VPN_IP_IFACE=tun0
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Steps to Secure Ubuntu Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/13/quick-steps-to-secure-ubuntu-linux/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T14:41:12+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/11/13/quick-steps-to-secure-ubuntu-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I&rsquo;ve been reviewing security and realised I&rsquo;ve been relying too much on my routers firewall - which isn&rsquo;t even present if I work on an open wifi connection somewhere.</p>

<p>Steps so far</p>

<p>Reinstalled Ubuntu with full disk encryption, apart from the need to back and restore data this was a painless process. I don&rsquo;t see a noticeable performance impact (though I have a fast system with SSD) the biggest drawback I can see is that if I mess around with a custom kernel and break the boot sequence - I don&rsquo;t know if I can boot from a live CD to fix it.</p>

<p>Setup a restrictive local firewall</p>

<p>as root</p>

<pre><code class="bash ">iptables -A INPUT -m conntrack --ctstate ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
iptables -I INPUT 1 -i lo -j ACCEPT
iptables -P INPUT DROP
iptables -S
apt-get install iptables-persistent
</code></pre>

<p>edit /etc/postfix/main.cf</p>

<p>set</p>

<p>inet_interfaces = 127.0.0.1</p>

<p>and <code>/etc/init.d/postfix restart</code></p>

<p>I will review open ports each time I configure a new service and ensure I don&rsquo;t have services I only need local accessible externally.</p>

<p>By both configuring firewall <strong>and</strong> limiting services I am applying the principle of defence in depth and even if there is a weakness (or I make a mistake) in one place I will still be protected.</p>

<p>Where I do need to share services between systems on my home/office network I have realised my old router is not sophisticated enough and am purchasing one that can separate secure and insecure networks.</p>

<p>All systems are now being configured for automatic updates, since I want patches as soon as possible, small frequent updates are easier to debug than problems with large updates, and generally I only delay updating out of inertia rather than any deliberate action. This way I don&rsquo;t even have to think about it.</p>

<p>from  <a href="http://www.richud.com/wiki/Ubuntu_Enable_Automatic_Updates_Unattended_Upgrades">http://www.richud.com/wiki/Ubuntu_Enable_Automatic_Updates_Unattended_Upgrades</a></p>

<p>my config files are now</p>

<pre><code class="bash">cat /etc/apt/apt.conf.d/50unattended-upgrades  | grep -v ^//
Unattended-Upgrade::Allowed-Origins {
    "${distro_id}:${distro_codename}-security";
    "${distro_id}:${distro_codename}-updates";
};
Unattended-Upgrade::Package-Blacklist {
};
Unattended-Upgrade::MinimalSteps "true";
Unattended-Upgrade::Mail "root";
Unattended-Upgrade::Remove-Unused-Dependencies "false";
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="bash">cat /etc/apt/apt.conf.d/10periodic  | grep -v ^//
APT::Periodic::Update-Package-Lists "1";
APT::Periodic::Download-Upgradeable-Packages "1";
APT::Periodic::AutocleanInterval "7";
APT::Periodic::Unattended-Upgrade "1";
APT::Periodic::Verbose "2";
APT::Periodic::RandomSleep "1";
</code></pre>

<p>Also set /root/.forward to ensure I get root mail</p>

<p>I have also realised I rely too much on browser stored passwords, and while this is useful for low-security logins I will not be using it for any important site.</p>

<p>Funnily I&rsquo;ve also found I needed to revisit my backup policy and actually delete more stuff <strong>not</strong> backing up code and documents which are business confidential and are already backed up centrally. In this case I realised my own backups were just causing a data management problem just increasing the risk that the data gets accidentally disclosed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu 10.04 Bluetooth Audio]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/10/06/ubuntu-10-04-bluetooth-audio/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/10/06/ubuntu-10-04-bluetooth-audio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It wasn&rsquo;t immediately obvious to me</p>

<p>What I needed to do to get blutooth audio working was to install the blueman package</p>

<p>After that configuration via GUI was pretty straightforward</p>

<p>Now I have fantastic sound via my bluetooth enabled HIFI :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu on a Samsung N150 Netbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/09/06/ubuntu-on-a-samsung-n150-netbook/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/09/06/ubuntu-on-a-samsung-n150-netbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Installing Ubuntu on a new netbook proved remarkably easy once I got past a couple of hurdles
</p>


<ul>
    <li>BIOS settings - in order to install a new OS I needed to configure the BIOS to boot from a USB key. At first it seemed like the netbook didn&#8217;t offer this option and I found several posts online from people having similar problems - but posts from others who had succeeded encouraged me and in the end I just had to guess the right points in the boot sequence to press the escape key and see a BIOS menu</li>
    <li>Bootable USB key, I followed the instructions at http://www.ubuntu.com/desktop/get-ubuntu/download but no matter what the USB key wouldn&#8217;t boot.<br />
    So I repartitioned and reformatted it on an existing Linux system, ran the USB Installer software again and this time it worked.</li>
    <li>Wireless network driver, I needed to update the system (over a wired network) before this worked - just following onscreen prompts.</li>
</ul>


<p>
As far as I can see everything now works (video, audio, webcam, wifi, power management etc)
</p>


<p>
I have a dev version of my current web project running with MySQL and Apache, MP3s play, I have a full office suite and all the utilities I could wish for.
</p>


<p>
I was impressed by the USB installers live mode allowing me to run Linux on the system before installing it fully, and then to repartition the hard drive leaving me with a dual boot system.
</p>


<p>
I wasn&#8217;t impressed with Windows though - very slow to get up and running (an hour of installs, updates and reboots - on a pre-installed system?!)  Constant alerts from the security software - and no useful software installed on the base system.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving an Svn Repository to Integrate With Trac]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/02/02/moving-an-svn-repository-to-integrate-with-trac/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/02/02/moving-an-svn-repository-to-integrate-with-trac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just started on a project that was using trac and subversion but they weren&#8217;t integrated. I love the cross referncing trac provides. It can really help explain changesets and show how an issue was resolved.</p>




<p>The steps to add subversion to trac are</p>




<ul>
<li>Stop people using the old repository</li>
<li>copy the repository files from one server to the other<br />I used tar and scp</li>
<li>edit trac.ini to add the location of the respository <br/>
Trac and svn must be on the same server</li>
<li>run trac-admin resync <br/>
This imports all the svn history.</li>
</ul>




<p><p>I enabled access to subversion via apache SSL while I could get access via the browser checking out code with different tools gave the follwoing errors</p>

<p><code>
svn: OPTIONS of &lsquo;<a href="https://195.99.1.93/svn">https://195.99.1.93/svn</a>&rsquo;: 200 OK</p>

<p>svn: PROPFIND of &lsquo;/svn&rsquo;: 405 Method Not Allowed</p>

<p>svn: Server sent unexpected return value (405 Method Not Allowed) in response to PROPFIND request for &lsquo;/svn&rsquo;
</code></p>

<p><p>Thanks to <a href="http://techpulp.com/2009/01/webdav-405-method-not-allowed-in-porpfind/">techpulp.com/2009/01/webdav-405-method-not-allowed-in-porpfind/</a> I found out that my problem was an extraneous trailing slash in my apache config!</p></p>

<p><p>I then ran svn relocate (right click on the repository using eclipse in the subversion perspective).</p></p>

<p><p>I moved Trac to SSL for good measure - changing the location on the task repository in eclipse was straightforward.</p></p>

<p><p>And as a finishing touch I customised Trac by adding a project logo - it goes in trac/htdocs/mylogo.png and is referenced in trac.ini as site/mylogo.png - I&rsquo;ve failed this step before but actuallt read the docs this tim.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
