<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Octopress | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-09T17:23:39+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Insert Line to All Files When Missing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/10/22/insert-line-to-all-files-when-missing/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T16:31:31+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/10/22/insert-line-to-all-files-when-missing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this case to turn on comments in all posts for this blog</p>

<p>All files that don&rsquo;t have comments at the start of a line get &ldquo;comments: true&rdquo; inserted on the 5th line</p>

<pre><code class="bash">for f in * ; do grep -q "^comments" $f || sed -i '5 i\
comments: true' $f ; done
</code></pre>

<p>Maybe Octopress has a way to globally enable comments - but I didn&rsquo;t find it and this was quick</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating From Drupal 5 to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/10/21/migrating-from-drupal-5-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T15:41:17+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2014/10/21/migrating-from-drupal-5-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been running this blog (or some version of it) for almost 10 years now.</p>

<p>I write to help clarify my own thoughts, or to note down technical details of a task that I have struggled to figure out. I often found myself coming back and have saved many hours of trying to figure out the same thing again a year or more later.</p>

<p>For a long time this site was running Drupal 5, I set it up at a time when I was getting to know Drupal, starting out as an independant, and had plenty of time to spend on it. At the time this was a very useful excercise, installing lots of modules, and writing some code was good experience. But when Drupal 6 came out and I was busy <a href="/blog/2008/07/18/time-to-upgrade-to-drupal-6}">it wasnt worth upgrading</a>, then when drupal 7 was released and Drupal 5 no longer supported, upgrading was even more difficult as I would have had to upgrade in two steps. Besides Drupal didn&rsquo;t seem like such a good fit for my blog any more.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t want to have to apply security updates on a site I&rsquo;m not getting paid for: so a static html site is a great fit for me.</p>

<p>I lose integrated comments, but spam had already killed those for me - I&rsquo;ll try disqus and see how that goes (the need to enable comments in the yaml for each post threw me at first).</p>

<p>Search was useful - but I can grep the source files myself.</p>

<p>I had all sorts of Drupal plugins before - but really I don&rsquo;t think they were very important.</p>

<p>Jekyll seems great, especially because with github&rsquo;s patronage it seems unlikely to become unsupported; and at the end of the day it is just a bunch of simple files so importing to another system should be easy.</p>

<p>Exporting from Drupal 5 needed a <a href="https://github.com/practicalweb/jekyll-import/commit/cfa72281147fd37ce527d2dab1f3ae916e066b04">small patch on the importer</a> without this the categories were seen as some kind of binary object in yaml. The import reads direct from the database, so doesn&rsquo;t run all Drupal&rsquo;s filters and I suspect a drupal export module from drupal would do a much better job. I still need to pull over some old comments and formatting could do with a tidy up, but I need to move to a system that gets me writing new content, and not worry too much about the old.</p>

<p>Jekyll itself didn&rsquo;t use tags in the way I wanted - I find the ability to cross link from one post to similar ones very useful so I am using Octopress which seem to do what I want out of the box.</p>

<p>To get the content in Octopress I just did</p>

<pre><code class="bash">cp jekyll/mysite/_posts/* octopress/source/_posts
</code></pre>

<p>I have switched from pygments highlighter to linguist (this seems to be what github use and supports code highlighting well)</p>

<p>I added a twitter aside for which I just copy pasted the twitter widget into <code>source/_includes/asides/twitter.html</code> and enabled this in _config.yml</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a ruby coder, so instaling all the required ruby gems and figuring out how to run a modified version of the jekyll importer took a little while, in the end I think it was just a case of getting all the gems installed that I needed. I didn&rsquo;t blog soon enough!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
