<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gis | PracticalWeb Ltd]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/categories/gis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-31T16:31:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Burlington]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OS Open Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/04/01/os-open-data/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/blog/2010/04/01/os-open-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
For several years I worked as a web developer for <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/">the Ramblers</a> and this experience very much colours my view of <a href="http://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/opendata">todays release</a> of free maps and postcode data.
</p>


<p>
This is a fantastic and significant step in the direction of ensuring that some of the worlds best mapping assets do the most good for society as a whole.
</p>


<p>
It will no doubt lead to an explosion of new applications and innovations.
</p>


<p>
Not least I expect we&#8217;ll see much better maps being used everywhere that couldn&#8217;t previously negotiate an OS license - not only were licenses expensive they were notoriously unclear.
</p>


<p>
However I can see why <a href="http://www.ramblers.org.uk/news/latest_news/OSfreemaps">the Ramblers are unhappy</a> at todays release   
</p>


<p>
If I want to show a map of a walk in the Lake district 
</p>


<p>
<img src="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/sites/default/files/u1/lakes1.jpeg" width="413" height="337" /> 
</p>


<p>
That&#8217;s the Lakes&#8230;
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>


<p>
<img src="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/sites/default/files/u1/lakes2.jpeg" width="384" height="322" /> 
</p>


<p>
Near Ulswater&#8230;
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>


<p>
<img src="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/sites/default/files/u1/lakes3.jpeg" width="446" height="338" /> 
</p>


<p>
It was from Glenridding up towards Helvelyn&#8230;
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>


<p>
<img src="http://www.practicalweb.co.uk/sites/default/files/u1/lakes4.jpeg" width="500" height="344" />
</p>


<p>
&#8230;Er.. yeah that&#8217;s the place - but where&#8217;s the path! 
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>


<p>
So this is a brilliant release and even for the Ramblers there&#8217;s loads of stuff they can do today that they either couldn&#8217;t do yesterday or it would have been more expensive and complex. 
</p>


<p>
And loads of smaller organisations will benefit from free maps and postcode data - these will become common on small websites.
</p>


<p>
But the release doesn&#8217;t quite give out the assets required to build the apps I always wanted to build for the Ramblers (walking routes, enhanced walks finder, path problem report tools etc). 
</p>


<p>
&nbsp;
</p>


<p>
Contains Ordnance Survey data (c) Crown copyright and database right 2010
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
